how to install IP-Tracer in Termux Without Root 
The IP address or internet protocol address is a unique address on the internet that specifically identifies your device on the internet. Everyone has a unique IP address, and that IP address contains some information about the device.
IP tracer is a great tool that allows you to trace anyone’s IP address and collect some extra information like country code, time zone city name Etc. You will also get longitude and latitude of the victim with the help of that coordinates you can find the location of the victim on the Google map. This location is not perfectly accurate but it will give you a rough idea about the location of the victim.
To use this tool we have to create a clone of the project from the GitHub repository the size of the project is very minimal. This tool is very helpful if you have victims IP address can you want to get some rough idea about the victim.
Install the Git package in your termux app to which will allow us to clone any project from the Github repository.
pkg install git -y
Type below command to clone the IP tracer project from the GitHub repository to your termux app.
🥺Please Visit the original Blog to Read All Steps :https://www.learntermux.tech/2020/02/how-to-install-ip-tracer-in-termux.html