👾 How to install Lazy Script in Termux — 2020 
In this post, I am going to tell you about a termux tool that is specially made for beginners.
Termux lazy script is a tool created by technical Mujeeb on GitHub that allows you to use termux in the laziest way. This tool will allow you to do tasks by selecting options. This is script is good for beginners because most of the beginners don’t know the commands, and this script will give them a list of options where they can select the task and it will do it without asking the command.
Termux lazy script is a basic tool that will have you with beginner-level things like showing I config result, it will tell your public IP, your architecture, storage info and user ID, it also contains 2 brute force tools which will help you with brute-forcing Hotmail and Yahoo which is not much useful in 2020. Some tools are not working but maybe it will get fixed after some time.
Some useful tools in the Termux-Lazy-Script are Heart-Bleed scanner, Public IP, Whois lookup. you can try them all one by one to see which tool is your favorite. If You are Intermediate or an advance Termux user, Don’t expect too much from this script.
Just Copy-Paste Below Commands One by one and Termux-Lazy-Script will be installed In your Termux app.
This command will check the dependencies and update them to the current date.
apt update && apt upgrade -y
Press Enter if asks about the version.
This command will install the python2 in git in your termux. Git package will be used to get the Lazy-script from the GitHub repository.
pkg install git python2 -y
Step 3:  The git-clone command will download the desired project from the GitHub repository.
Please Visit Orignal Blog for full post🥺 : https://www.learntermux.tech/2020/02/Install-Lazy-Script-in-Termux.html