How to Install Z-Shell The Best Theme For Termux-2020 
ZShell is a top-rated shell that will not only change the interface of your terminal but add some extra features to it. Z shell gives you the option to select from more than 40 color schemes.
Z shell is also useful to detect if your command is right and helps you to navigate easily by showing available options. The left side of your cursor will show the path you are in. If multiple sessions are open in your termux app every session will have a unique name and it will help you to select the correct terminal and you don’t have to open every session one by one find the correct session.
You can also change the font in Zshell you can switch to a new theme whenever you want by just typing a single command. Z shell is a project on GitHub which is created by 4679 on GitHub.
This command will check the pre-installed packages and update them to the current date.
apt update && apt upgrade
Press N if you ask about the version.
This command will install the git package which will allow us to download Zshell project from the GitHub repository.
pkg install git
(While installing if it is asking “do you wanna install” just press y and Enter.)
Step 3:  the git-clone command will download the Zshell project from the GitHub repository.
git clone https://github.com/khansaad1275/termux-ohmyzsh
Please Visit Orignal Blog to read Full Steps: https://www.learntermux.tech/2020/02/how-to-install-z-shell-best-theme-for-TERMUX-2020.html