How to get someones IP-Address using Termux — 2020 
An IP address is a unique address of a device on the internet. Since everyone has a unique IP address, therefore we can find some interesting information about the victim using the IP address off the device using.
In this post, I am going to guide you on how you can Grab someone’s IP address by just sending a link. If the victim clicks the Link it’s guaranteed that you will get the IP address of the victim. After getting the IP address of the victim we can trace information about that IP like the location of the IP address, which city belongs to and zip code etc.
You can even use IP stressors that will stop the incoming and outgoing traffic for that particular IP address this can be beneficial if you want to prevent something bad from a specific IP address.
To find the IP address by sending a link we are going to use a tool called shellfish we can use this tool to do phishing attacks I have a complete post on [ How to do phishing attack using shellfish To hack anyones Social media account], but in this post, we are going to use this tool as IP Logger. This tool will create a link which we will have to send to the victim, after victim Clicks on the link we will get the IP address on the terminal. This tool uses port forwarding to achieve this task. I am not going to waste your time and give you step by step guide I have combined all commands in one big command.
Install ShellPhish To Grab IP-Address:
copy-paste this command and this tool will be installed on your system.. This tool will download wget and Git package in termux and then shelphish tool will download from the GitHub repository and allow the executable permission to the shellphish.sh file.
Please Visit Orignal Blog to Read Full Blog : https://www.learntermux.tech/2020/02/Get-IP-Address-using-Termux.html