How to Learn Python programming using Termux — 2020 
Termux is a great tool that allows you to do hacking on you android phone one of the best thing about the termux app is that it allows you to install and run python on your android phone.
Python is a high-level interpreted language created by Guido van Rossum. If you are thinking about learning a programming language in 2020 python is the best language I can suggest. you can create tools that will allow you to simplify your work python is easy to learn and if you are thinking about learning it using termux then this post is for you.
Using termux you can learn intermediate level python programming you can research on external moduls of python that will allow you to create some really useful projects. If you are really serious about python then I will suggest you learn from multiple sources and learn topic wise.
Termux is portable. When you start learning to program you get new ideas while you are not at your desk if you are working on some project then you certainly realize how you can solve that bug you were stuck from the past few days. Using termux you can code anywhere and even without internet so as long is python package is in your termux app you can code in Python language no matter where you are.
You can download a certain project from the internet and then paste it into your termux app and then you can execute it. You can attach a physical keyboard with your phone and then it will be more easy to do programming on your phone.
Please Visit orignal Blog for full Post (trust me you will never regret clicking this link):https://www.learntermux.tech/2020/02/how-to-learn-python-programming-using-Termux.html