Python - Termux Wiki
Python is an interpreted, high-level, general-purpose programming language. Created by Guido van Rossum and first released in 1991, Python's design philosophy emphasizes code readability with its notable use of significant whitespace. Its language constructs and object-oriented approach aim to help programmers write clear, logical code for small and large-scale projects. 
In Termux Python can be installed by executing  
pkg install python  
Legacy, deprecated version 2.7.x can be installed by  
pkg install python2   
Package management 
After installing Python, pip (pip2 if using python2) package manager will be available. Here is a quick tutorial about its usage. 
Installing a new Python module:  
pip install {module name}  
Uninstalling Python module:  
pip uninstall {module name}  
Listing installed modules:  
pip list  
When installing Python modules, it is highly recommended to have a package build-essential to be installed - some modules compile native extensions during their installation.  
Python module installation tips and tricks 
It is assumed that you have build-essential or at least clang, make and pkg-config installed. 
It also assumed that termux-exec is not broken and works on your device. Environment variable LD_PRELOAD is not tampered or unset. Otherwise you will need to patch modules' source code to fix all shebangs!   
Advanced installation instructions 
Some Python modules may not be easy to install. Here are collected information on how to get them available in your Termux.  
Numpy and Scipy 
Building complex software like numpy and scipy is tedious. Therefore, Termux user its-pointless (aka live_the_dream) has packaged this software and maintain a Termux APT repository with these and many other useful packages. 
Before Numpy/Scipy installation, you need to subscribe to APT repository:  
curl -LO https://its-pointless.github.io/setup-pointless-repo.sh bash setup-pointless-repo.sh  
Then you can install Numpy or Scipy like a regular Termux package:  
pkg install numpy pkg install scipy  
OpenCV 
Instructions taken from #512 and #1992. OpenCV is not a Python package but it includes the Python bindings (known as opencv-python in pip). 
OpenCV needs to be built from source using CMake, install it and other dependencies with:  
pkg install build-essential cmake libjpeg-turbo libpng python  
Numpy is also required, see instructions for installing it above. 
There might be other required dependecies as well, see the OpenCV docs for the list. 
The rest of the instructions can be copy-pasted straight away, but if you are not sure if you have all dependencies then it might be best to do it in two steps: first all commands up until the LDFLAGS=" -llog" cmake command and then in a second step make and make install. 
To get the sources, git clone (from a suitable folder):  
git clone https://github.com/opencv/opencv cd opencv  
You should now be in the opencv folder. Let's create a build folder where we will build the package:  
mkdir build cd build  
To configure the package for python3 but not python2 (change the on/off flags to use python2 instead of python3) we run:  
LDFLAGS=" -llog -lpython3" cmake -DCMAKE_BUILD_TYPE=RELEASE -DCMAKE_INSTALL_PREFIX=$PREFIX -DBUILD_opencv_python3=on -DBUILD_opencv_python2=off -DWITH_QT=OFF -DWITH_GTK=OFF ..  
Last command will throw errors if there are missing dependencies. After this we can compile the package with  
make  
and then install the files with  
make install  
Tkinter 
Tkinter is splitted of from the python package and can be installed by  
pkg install python-tkinter  
We do not provide Tkinter for Python v2.7.x. 
Since Tkinter is a graphical library, it will work only if X Windows System environment is installed and running. How to do this, see page Graphical Environment.  
Installing Python modules from source 
Some modules may not be installable without patching. They should be installed from source code. Here is a quick how-to about installing Python modules from source code. 
1. Obtain the source code. You can clone a git repository of your package:  
git clone https://your-package-repo-url cd ./your-package-repo  
or download source bundle with pip:  
pip download {module name} unzip {module name}.zip cd {module name}  
2. Optionally, apply the desired changes to source code. There no universal guides on that, perform this step on your own. 
3. Optionally, fix the all shebangs. This is not needed if termux-exec is installed and works correctly.  
find . -type f -not -path '*/\.*' -exec termux-fix-shebang "{}" \;  
4. Finally install the package:  
python setup.py install     