Termux:Boot - Termux Wiki
This addon will run scripts immediately after device was booted.  
Installation 
F-Droid 
Google Play 
Important: Do not mix installations of Termux and Addons between Google Play and F-Droid. They are presented at these portals for your convenience. There are compatibility issues when mixing installations from these Internet portals. This is because each download website uses a specific key for keysigning Termux and Addons.  
Usage 
1. Install the Termux:Boot app. 
2. Start the Termux:Boot app once by clicking on its launcher icon. This allows the app to be run at boot. 
3. Create the ~/.termux/boot/ directory: Put scripts you want to execute inside the ~/.termux/boot/ directory. If there are multiple files, they will be executed in a sorted order. Note that you may want to run termux-wake-lock as first thing if you want to ensure that the device is prevented from sleeping. 
Example: to start an sshd server and prevent the device from sleeping at boot, create the following file at ~/.termux/boot/start-sshd:  
#!/data/data/com.termux/files/usr/bin/sh termux-wake-lock sshd  
If you want Termux-services to start services on boot, you can use:  
#!/data/data/com.termux/files/usr/bin/sh termux-wake-lock . $PREFIX/etc/profile     